Insulin resistance is a major health
risk that is the foundation of type two
diabetes and general metabolic syndrome
because the hormone insulin needs to
bind to our cells to trigger them to
take up glucose, fats, and even amino
acids from the protein. The more
sensitive to insulin that your cells
are, the less insulin is needed to bind
to cells and remove the nutrients from
the blood to feed the cells of your
body. Insulin resistance does the exact
opposite. Since the cells are resistant
to insulin, they are bound yet nothing
happens. In response, the pancreas
releases more insulin to strengthen the
activating signal and the cycle
continues as insulin levels must get
higher and higher to achieve the same
effect. It's detrimental to the pancreas
and detrimental to the circulatory
system and tissues as blood glucose
eventually rises causing a host of
problems. Okay, so let's say you decide
that you want to improve your insulin
sensitivity avoiding the issue entirely
and you jump on a diet. The question is,
would you be better served doing
something in addition to that diet?
Let's find out. This information isn't
new on the face of it, but there are
several impactful points that
researchers uncovered in a study wherein
they allocated one group of overweight
insulin resistance people to a dietonly
condition following a preditin style
diet designed to be calorically
restricted. And the other group was to
follow the same diet but include
exercise. Ultimately, they wanted to
find out how much impact diet alone has
and how much impact doing a combination
of diet and exercise can have over a
five-month period. But they also uncover
something unique that I want to share
with you, too. If we pop open the
initial data, I realize this looks like
a lot, and it is, but I'm going to
highlight the key findings, and
especially one that has an intriguing
story behind it, although it might not
seem that way initially. So we have the
two group conditions up top and the p
values on the right side. If they fall
below 0.05, that means there's a
difference between the groups. On the
left, we clearly see the measurements.
So I'd like to point out just a few,
though. One, look at the body fat
percentage and the body mass. They're
roughly the same at the start of the
study. And although they both reduced
over the five months, they were there
were no differences between the groups.
That's important because one could argue
that exercise on top of diet could lead
to greater weight loss and fat loss,
which might be the explanation for any
differences that we might see. However,
that's off the table. Now, now number
two, this is where the plot thickens
because if we look at the blood glucose
values and the insulin values, we see
that blood glucose was not different
between groups. Yet, insulin was reduced
more with the exercise group. This of
course gives us a clue that a per
molecule of insulin more glucose is
being taken out of the circulation. A
strong indication of insulin
sensitivity, reduced insulin resistance.
Okay, great. But we've seen these kinds
of data before. So what's so unique
about this study? Well, the researchers
did some unique tests to find out
exactly how exercise provides this
benefit, which I thought were really
informative to a unique effect that
exercise has. The researchers did a
24-hour measure of blood glucose and
insulin after consuming multiple
standardized meals to assess how the
body reacts to food over 24 hours. If we
look at the insulin levels on the left,
we have the spikes and valleys of
insulin released from the pancreas over
24 hours. On the right, we have the AU
or the area under the curve, which
indicates the overall amount of insulin
secreted. The white dots represent the
baseline before each intervention and
then the diet or diet plus exercise. The
dark dots are after 5 months of each
intervention. Now, unfortunately, the
researchers only did between group
comparisons. So, we can only fairly
compare the insulin levels between the
diets and the diet plus exercise. But we
can't fairly compare within group
comparisons like before the diet and
after the diet. That's important because
we might be tempted to look at the diet
condition and say there's no difference,
but we don't have the statistics to say
one way or another. However, we can say
that because of the asterisk there that
the exercise addition condition
experienced a significant reduction in
insulin compared to the dieting alone.
That's not altogether extremely new
considering that we knew that from the
previous data, although differently
collected, but check this out here.
We're looking at insulin secretion. So,
the amount of insulin released by the
pancreas. Note that there's no asterisk
and that's because there's no
difference. So, if the pancreas is
releasing the same amount of insulin,
how is insulin so much lower in the
exercise condition? Oh man, look at the
time. Let's ignore the fact that I don't
have a watch on. I must impart to you a
fair bit of good news. Did thou know
that I'll be covering more on liver
insulin sensitivity as well as more on
the diets and exercise and the effects
on mitochondria in the extended version
of this video that you're watching?
Well, now you know that isn't even to
mention the live sessions with me, the
insider podcast and the oh yes, insider
that refers to the physionic insiders of
which you could be a member and access
all the goodness. It's in the
description box if you're so inclined.
So, if the pancreas is releasing the
same amount of insulin and how is
insulin so much lower in the exercise
condition, deja vu anyone? Well, just
like any equation of the sort, we've
addressed what increases insulin, but we
haven't covered what removes insulin.
Insulin is taken up by the liver and the
kidneys through receptors that bind it
and then endoccytos, meaning that the
receptor with the insulin bound will be
taken up into the cell. Then it's
degraded. Since secretion is roughly the
same, there's more to say on that front,
too, but let's not get distracted.
Insulin clearance must be increased. And
we find that to be the case. We clearly
see insulin clearance rate ICR increase
in the exercise condition. So somehow
exercise is increasing insulin
clearance. So it doesn't remain in the
blood explaining the significant
difference in blood insulin in the first
metric that we looked at. However,
there's a few things of note here. One,
while this study was well controlled in
certain respects, like making all the
food for the participants, it was not
randomized, which introduces risk of a
type of bias called selection bias. Two,
these results are in a small group of
overweight insulin resistant
individuals. So, we don't know if this
would apply to people who are overweight
but have the murmurings of insulin
resistance. Personally, I think it
would, but we don't know that for a
fact. Three, the participants consumed a
pritikinstyle diet, which is a very high
carbohydrate diet. Would uh we see
worse, similar, or better results using
another diet type that also provides a
caloric deficit? We don't know. And like
I said, this isn't the first study to
indicate exercise is a benefit. No news
there. But what is unique is how and the
overall effect. We now know that
assuming that this maintains in other
studies that diet alone might provide
benefit but pairing it with exercise has
a substantially greater effect in
overweight insulin resistant
individuals. We also know that exercise
reduces insulin in the blood more
drastically and it does that through
ramping up the liver or kidney or both
to metabolize insulin. In fact, there's
more on the topic right here if you're
so inclined. Thanks for hanging out.
[Music]